# 大家好 今天搞了一點田螺回來哦
Hi everyone! I got some river snails back today.
# 準備炒田螺吃
We're gonna make some fried river snails.
# 要搞點這個山胡椒 (註︰他這裡說山胡椒，之後說野胡椒，不管了，就當是山上的胡椒算了)
I gotta fetch some wild pepper.
# 山胡椒搞點下來 你看
Wild pepper., let's fetch some. Look!
# 上面就好多
There's a lot up there.
# 把它勾點下來就好啦
I only need to hook some down here.
# 你看 一下子就搞了那麼多
Look! I can get so much with just a single pull.
# 吃不完的等下用來曬乾
The rest can be dried if we can't finish them.
# 下去 炒田螺 (註︰這裡說得太明白感覺極奇怪，所以starts cooking算了)
Let's go, and start cooking.
# 我們把這個果子摘下來 摘下來然後就
We first pick all the fruits here, pick them all and then we can,
# 用油炸一下 這個味道就全部出來啦
fry them in the oil. Then the flavour will all come out,
# 山胡椒的味道
The scent of wild pepper,
# 很香的哦
is really nice, you know.
# 小時候我們
When we were small,
# 摘來賣 現在都沒人要啦 山上到處都是
we used to sell them. But now nobody wants them anymore. They're everywhere on the hills.
# 以前一毛錢一斤摘來賣
We sold them at 1 jiao (0.1 RMB) per 500 grams in the past.
# 每天能摘個一塊錢
And we could have up to 1 RMB in a day.
# 那時候一塊錢可以買很多糖啦
Back in those days, we could buy a lot of candies with 1 RMB.
# 你看 摘了那麼一點 夠啦
Look! I've picked just a bit here. It's enough.
# 要洗一下 洗一下晾乾 等一下
We need to wash it, wash it and then dry it, and then,
# 就直接可以用啦
it can be used right away.
# 你看 這是攝影小哥的
Look! These are Mr. Cameraman's
# 私人小物品
private little kits.
# 在底下
At the bottom
# 誒呀
Eya!
# 這個 給這個鉗子給你
This, this pincer is for you.
# 好
'kay
# 這個甚麼鬼
What the heck is it?
# 這個剪毛的
Is it for cutting hair?
# 這裡還有把
Here's one more.
# 打開來看
Let me open it and have a look.
# 這個尖鉗
It's a sharp pincer.
# 夠了 那麼多個鉗子
Enough. We have so many pincers now.
# 幾個人一起來剪 剪得快一點 (註︰同樣是說明"cut"的話，感覺很突冗)
Let's do it together with several of us. It takes much less time.
# 我要這個最猛的
I take this most powerful one.
# 你看 這個鉗子好剪 哎呀
Look! This pincer is really effective. Aya!
# 洗一下這個田螺 這個田螺剪好啦
Let's wash the river snails. They've all been processed.
# 再洗一下
Wash a few more times.
# 好啦 洗好啦 我們煮一下水喲
Alright! They're clean now. We're gonna boil them in water for a while.
# 要把水煮一下
They needs to be boiled in water for a while.
# 裝點水 煮一下這個田螺 然後再來炒
Take some water, and boil the snails for a while. And then we can fry them.
# 那才沒那麼腥
So that they won't smell so fishy.
# 水太多了
Too much water
# 搞點這個香料下去
Put some spice,
# 把它臭味遮住
to cover up the bad odour.
# 你看 再煮一下 好像火候還不是很夠
Look! It doesn't seem long enough. Let's boil it for a longer while.
# 你看 這個煮好了哦
Look! It's alright now.
# 我去那個 我去洗一下
I'm gonna, I mean, I'm gonna wash it.
# 這樣搓一下就把這個瞉 你看 就整個掉下來啦
As I'm rubbing it, the shell, look, the whole piece of shell comes off.
# 先把鍋燒開
Let me heat the wok first,
# 然後放油
and then put the oil.
# 生薑去炸一下
Ginger, let me fry it.
# 再把這個
And then I put the,
# 野胡椒
wild pepper,
# 哎喲 好香哦
Ayo! It smells so good!
# 搞點這個八角
Put some, this is star anise.
# 好 準備放田螺啦
Alright! Time for the river snails
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 鹽都沒放
I didn't even put salt.
# 放鹹一點
A bit more salt
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 聞都聞得那個味道
The smell is already confirming the taste.
# 丟幾個辣椒下去
Let me throw some chilli in.
# 這裡還有辣椒粉哦 再搞點下去
Here's also some chilli powder. Let me put some as well.
# 沒事 攝影小哥不喜歡吃田螺
No worries. Mr. Cameraman doesn't like river snails.
# 誒 多啦
Ey? Too much
# 這裡還有點乾辣椒
Here's also some dried chilli.
# 再放點這個醬油
Put some, some soy sauce too.
# 你看 顏色就出來啦
Look! The colour is coming out now.
# 色香味俱全
It pleases your eyes, your nose and your tastes bud as well.
# 先去把一下 看還有甚麼好放的 順便放下去
Let me have a look around, and see if there's anything good, and put them here all along.
# 你看 剛好還有點黃酒
Look! I just see that we have some huangjiu (yellow rice wine) here as well.
# 搞點黃酒下去
Let me put some huangjiu.
# 在廚房找了一個大蒜
And I got a garlic in the kitchen.
# 大蒜也扔下去算啦
Let me just throw the garlic in.
# 拍一下就好
Smash it, that's it!
# 這有幾個大蒜
Here's some garlic.
# 哎呀 越來越香啦放點水下去
Aya! The scent is getting more and more attractive.
# 加點水
Put some water.
# 把它燜 煮熟它
And then stew it, cook it.
# 放點水
Put some water.
# 誒 鍋呢
Eh? Where's the pot?
# 搞了點山泉水來燜
I've fetched some spring water to the stew.
# 燜個半個小時
Stew it for half and hour,
# 這田螺就可以吃啦
and then I can start my feast.
# 應該熟了哦 看一下
I think it's done now. Let me have a look.
# 看上去就好吃
It looks really tasty.
# 裝不下啦
The plate is full.
# 下一盤
Next plate...
# 看 吃這盤就好啦
Look! This plate is already enough for me.
# 這盤我的
And this plate is my,
# 晚上我來吃
one of the dishes of my dinner.
# 哎呀 到這裡來吸
Aya! Let me enjoy it here.
# 你看 這個葉子
Look! This leave...
# 漂亮吧
Pretty, isn't it?
# 瞬間上檔次
It becomes fine dining instantly.
# 哎呀 很燙
Aya! Hot!
# 這個
The,
# 田螺瞉把
the shells can be used to,
# 餵魚
feed the fish.
# 哇 真的很好吃哦 就是有點辣
Wa! It's really tasty. But it's a rather spicy.
# 一個田螺就那麼一點點肉
The edible part of a river snail is just a tiny little bit here.
# 好辣
Burning!
# 真的很辣哦 這個辣椒
It's really spicy, this kind of chilli.
# 好啦 今天視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 反正攝影小哥又吃不了
Mr. Cameraman can't stand it anyway.
# 太辣啦
It's far too spicy.